# CURRICULUM VITAE: KENNETH SMITH

TEL: 082 893 0700 EMAIL: kag.smith@gmail.com

**PRIVATE & CONFIDENTIAL** 

# PERSONAL INFORMATION

Kenneth (Ken) Albert Gascoine Smith Name

Identity number 7802285217081

28 February 1978 Date of Birth

Marital Status Married with one dependent

Nationality South African

English (fully bilingual) Languages

Afrikaans

Criminal offences Nil

Driver's License Code 08 – Own reliable transport

Health Excellent

Postal address PO Box 2097

Faerie Glen

0043

Residential 3 Blue Crane Villas

Wierda Crest Estate

Centurion

#### INTRODUCTION

I am currently an Account Manager with 9+ years' sales and marketing experience across various industries including IT & Process Engineering, Real Estate and Travel & Tourism. I have also owned and managed my own company early in my career and have worked in corporate environments ever since then. The common thread across the industries I've specialised in has been building and maintaining strong and sustainable customer relationships and ensuring that I clearly understand customer requirements during the sales process.

My motto in life is the fact that integrity is the foundation upon which all other values are built. I stay true to this motto in both business and my personal life.

# Unique qualities/Core competencies applied in the workplace

I have applied the following qualities in the workplace to ensure I add value to the organisation and increase overall business:

- Ensure I do not overcomplicate things and keep communication to co-workers and customers clear, accurate and informative.
- Always ensure that benefits/niche concepts the organisation I work for has is communicated to the market to create and maintain exposure and credibility.
- Ensure I truly connect with co-workers and customers as this is key in developing and sustaining solid relationships.
- Ensure my turnaround time in getting answers to people is guick to keep momentum and stimulate potential business emerging from this.
- Stand out from the competition by understanding exactly what they have to offer and to counter this by connecting with the customer first and pointing out what additional features and advantages the company I work for has to offer.
- Stay abreast of latest events and developments in the media at all times to have full awareness of what's happening in the market in general. This has worked well in the past identifying potential business opportunities.
- Always ensure every customer feels his/her guery is the most important and attended to accordingly. It has been incredible how this added to relationship building during my career thus
- Ensure "grey" areas are turned into black and white so everyone involved is fully aware of their responsibilities and duties to function successfully and efficiently.
- Being a true ambassador for the company I represent at all times as this reflects to customers the credibility of the company they are conducting business with.

#### **CAREER HISTORY**

#### Company

# **BLUESP (PTY) LTD (JUNE 2008 – CURRENT)**

#### **Position**

# Account Manager

#### Responsibilities/Functions

- Build new account as well as further expand existing account.
- Identify trends and opportunities in new markets to distribute software solutions and consulting services to.
- Build relationships with new customers and maintain existing relationships.
- Manage key accounts within the MMM (mining, metals and minerals), Engineering & Construction and Petrochemical industries including customers such as Anglo Platinum, Columbus Stainless, Sasol, Samancor Ferrochrome, Xstrata and Impala Platinum.
- Identify and communicate the competitive edge of our products and services.
- Interpret legal agreements between the company and its customers
- Negotiate software and services pricing, Service Level Agreements, terms of contract and consulting services delivery with suppliers and customers.
- Prospect, initiate, negotiate and close deals of varying sizes and complexity.
- Participate in tender proposal structuring and attend tender clarification sessions.
- Report to top management monthly on sales updates, trends, initiatives and sales numbers.
- Sales target: this can be disclosed on request due to the confidential nature thereof.

#### Successes

- TCTA, Group 5, Sasol, Grinaker LTA, Cosira Group, ESKOM, Shaft Sinkers deals (Oracle services and software)
- BHP Billiton Metalloys deal (AspenTech MES software and services)
- Bateman deal (Oracle services and software)
- Anglo Platinum token deal (AspenTech APC software)
- Impala Platinum deal (Aspentech MES software and SLA)
- Xstrata SLA and LIMS deal (BluESP services)
- Columbus Stainless deal (AspenTech MES software and services)

# Additional courses completed

Enrolled and successfully completed the PROJECT MANAGEMENT FOR NON PROJECT MANAGER'S COURSE

#### Company

#### MORTGAGESA (OOBA) (MAY 2007 – MAY 2008)

#### **Position**

Sales & Technical Training officer and Material Developer

#### Responsibilities/Functions

- Sales training for national sales workforce
- Sales training including leadership, motivation, sales techniques, personality types, presentation skills, communication skills,

- teamwork and negotiation skills.
- Technical skills training to operate online customer detail capturing and processing system.
- Developed training material for sales staff based on sales principles of Stephen Covey and Richard Branson as well as leadership training based on the principles of John Maxwell.
- Financial Advisory and Intermediary Services Act (FAIS) training for sales staff.
- Arranged workshop days for sales staff.
- Engaged with sales staff within the sales environment.

#### Successes

- Established strong teamwork structures amongst regional sales staff.
- Communicated ideas around attracting more customers during times when business was down.
- Motivated regional sales staff to become creative in their sales approaches.
- Successfully trained and engaged with over 200 sales staff over a period of one year.

# Additional courses completed

Enrolled and successfully completed the DIMENSIONS OF PROFESSIONAL SELLING COURSE

#### Company

# PTC GROUP/HOSPITALITY PROFESSIONALS (SEPTEMBER 2004 - APRIL 2007)

#### **Position**

Travel and Tourism sales training, assessing, guiding training and material development

# Responsibilities/Functions

- Sales training for Ster-Kinekor management group (National Certificate in Management Leadership Programme)
- Sales and guiding training for the Department of Environmental Affairs and Tourism (Culture Guiding Skills Programme on how to sell one self and the resources South Africa has to offer)
- Material Development for the following courses: Advanced Nature Guiding Learnership on NQF level 4; Creating a guided nature experience for customers Skills Programme NOF Level 4; Conducting a guided nature experience for customers Skills Programme NQF Level 4; Conducting a guided marine experience for customers Skills Programme NOF Level 4
- Structured and conducted a skills audit across the entire Northern Cape Province that included an audit of hospitality establishments such as hotels, quest houses andbed and breakfasts. This gave me the opportunity to connect with tourism industry suppliers on the accommodation-side and assist them with better positioning their product in the market and also deliver better service to their customers.

#### Successes

Successfully delivered sales and guiding training to around 75

- individuals to see them complete their learnerships.
- Witnessed people transforming from shy, non-assertive individuals to motivated, confident individuals ready to sell the products and services of the companies they represent.
- Assisted tourism accommodation establishment owners to better market their establishments and increase their level of service delivery.

# Company

# **KQ's ADVENTURE TOURS, AFRICAN KALEIDOSCOPE TOURS AND** SAFARIS, APEX AFRICA TOURS AND SAFARIS (DECEMBER 2001 -**AUGUST 2004)**

#### **Position**

#### Owner

## Responsibilities/Functions

- All organisational marketing and sales
- International sales (UK, USA and European markets predominantly)
- Sales budget structuring and tourism package quotation structuring
- Marketing initiatives through travel agencies, accommodation suppliers, website, brochures and customer visits
- Customer and supplier relationship building
- Connecting with corporate travel organisations
- Negotiate STO rates, transport rates and accommodation rates
- Communication with staff, suppliers and customers
- Strategic planning and logistics

#### Successes

- Winning the UK Richmond Women's Rugby Tour contract 2003
- Being part of the organizational team for the World Summit Moroccan Delegation coordination 2003
- Winning the EDCON Roadshow transport contract 2004

#### **EDUCATION**

#### SECONDARY EDUCATION

Last school attended

#### PRETORIA BOYS HIGH SCHOOL

(PRETORIA) 1996

Highest grade passed

Grade 12 - Higher Grade

Subjects

English, Afrikaans, Mathematics, Business Economics, Biology, Physical Science

#### **TERTIARY EDUCATION**

#### **UNIVERSITY OF STELLENBOSCH**

1998

Institute attended

#### **B. COM MARKETING MANAGEMENT**

Degree course

Commercial Entrepreneurship

Subjects completed

- Computer Literacy I
- Ergonomics I
- Business Management (Financial Management, Marketing Management, Production Management)

Institute attended

#### UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA

1999-2001

Degree course

#### **B. COM TOURISM MANAGEMENT**

Subjects completed

- Marketing Management I,II,III
- Tourism Management I,II,III
- Business Management I,II,III
- Communication Management II,III
- Industrial psychology I
- Economics I
- Business law II

Special achievements

- One of the top Marketing Management students award (2000)
- Deputy Chairman: Tuks Tourism Students Association (2001)
- Joined first prize for best Tourism Project of the year award (1999)
- Second prize for best Tourism Project of the year award (2000 &
- Fidelio and Lanmark food and beverage management certificate (2001)
- Nature guiding skills certificate (2000)
- Basic catering skills certificate (2000)

Institute attended

#### **DRUM BEAT ACADEMY**

2002

Certificate course

#### **ADVANCED NATURE GUIDING LEVEL 6**

Unit standards passed

144 CREDITS

Provinces covered

MPUMALANGA & KWAZULU-NATAL PROVINCE

#### **COMPUTER LITERACY**

MS WORD MS OUTLOOK MS POWER POINT MS EXCEL

FIDELIO FRONT OFFICE

LANMARK

ONLINE PROCESSING SYSTEM (OPS) USED FOR BOND APPLICATION

CAPTURING THAT IS LINKED TO THE BANKS

# INTERNATIONAL EXPERIENCE (year after completing grade 12)

**COMPANY HSS EVENTS PLANNING** April 1997

Industry **Events Coordination Company** 

**EVENTS COORDINATOR** Position

**Duties** Site layout and structuring

Catering coordination

Security logistics

Staff orientation

**COMPANY LURGAN MARKS AND SPENCER SUPPLIER COMPANY** July 1997

Position Retail foods supply company

**PLANT OPERATIONS TRAINEE Duties** 

Machinery and equipment hygiene inspections

Food processing logistics

Food storage and department transfers of batches

Food transport logistics

Packaging specifics

**PERSONAL INTERESTS** 

People – interaction and connecting

Following current local and global news and events

Sport (golf, rugby)

Nature & outdoors

Global travel and tourism

**REFERENCES** Will provide details upon request